In these next few videos,
I'm going to be covering cholesterol-
lowering drugs like statins,
why LDL cholesterol
is such a major threat,
for whom the benefits of
these drugs outweigh the risks,
and what we can do to
lower our cholesterol naturally.
"Why Isn't Everyone on Cholesterol-
Lowering Statin Drugs?"
LDL cholesterol,
also known as bad cholesterol,
is unequivocally recognized
as the principal driving force
in the development
of atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease,
our leading cause of death.
Over the decades, we have seen
the guidelines shift
to lower and lower LDL targets
on the basis of clinical trials
demonstrating that lower
is better,
starting in the 1980s
with an LDL target of 130,
then down to a hundred
in the ’90s,
and maybe down to 70
for those at really high risk,
and then maybe even down
to 55, 40, or 30
over the last decade.
Those more recent targets
might actually be closer
to normal for the human species.
Even after we learned
to use tools so we could hunt,
normal LDL has been
in the 50 to 70 range,
but today, the average
in the Western world
is more like 120 mg/dL.
No wonder heart disease
is our leading cause of death
in men and women.
Recently, guidelines
started scrapping targets
in favor of just pushing
for LDL levels
to be as low as possible,
because the lower the better.
No threshold
seems to exist below
which LDL cholesterol-lowering
does not further reduce risk.
When it comes to LDL,
it’s possible
that lower is better
for longer,
even if you start out
at low risk.
The risk reduction
of major vascular events
is independent
of the starting LDL cholesterol,
meaning that even people
starting out
with an LDL under 80
had about the same relative
risk reduction.
So, even if your LDL
is quote-unquote "normal,"
even if other heart disease
risk factors
are considered optimal,
it’s considered
of utmost importance
to control it.
So, why not just put
cholesterol-lowering drugs
like statins
in the drinking water
like we do fluoride?
Why aren’t statins
prescribed for everyone?
Because of the downsides.
There’s the risk
of side effects,
plus the burden of having
to take a pill every day
for the rest of your life.
So, that’s why these drugs
are only recommended for people
at relatively high risk
of having a heart attack
for whom the pros
of cholesterol-lowering
outweigh the cons
of taking the drug.
Okay, but when it comes to LDL,
if "lower is better for longer,
and the earlier the better,"
and the only reason
we’re not giving more drugs
is the downsides,
what if there were
safe, simple,
side-effect-free solutions
to lowering our cholesterol,
for example,
eating specific types
of healthy foods every day?
Well, in that case, regardless
if we’re on drugs or not,
shouldn’t we utilize
every safe no-downside strategy
there is
to get our LDL
down as low as possible?
Before I get
to all those strategies,
let’s answer
the on-drugs-or-not question.
According to the latest
cholesterol
clinical practice guidelines
from the American
Heart Association
and the American College
of Cardiology,
the number one
take-home message
is a lifelong
heart-healthy lifestyle.
Okay, but when do
they also recommend drugs?
If you have been diagnosed
with heart disease,
like if you already
had a heart attack
and are trying
to prevent another one,
then drugs are considered
non-negotiable.
Okay, but what about
primary prevention,
meaning preventing
that first heart attack?
Well, if you have an LDL
of 190 or more,
then "don’t pass go,
don’t collect $200,"
go straight to statins.
Similarly, if you’re between 40
and 75 and have diabetes,
then an LDL of even 70
gets you a statin
recommendation.
Now, if you don’t have
known cardiovascular disease
or diabetes,
and your LDL is between 70
and 190,
then statins are
generally recommended
if your risk of having
a cardiovascular event,
like a heart attack or stroke,
is 7.5% or more
over the next ten years.
Here’s the flow chart
for primary prevention,
based on age, LDL,
diabetes status,
and ten-year risk.
You can pause
and work your way through it.
As you can see, even at
a ten-year risk as low as 5%,
a statin may be recommended
if you have
risk-enhancing factors
such as high triglycerides
or a bad family history.
And if you’re in that
intermediate risk category
where statins are recommended,
but you’re still on the fence,
a coronary calcium scan
imaging test
can be done to help you decide.
How do you figure out
what your ten-year risk is?
In a previous video
I did on the topic,
I recommended three
common risk calculators,
but I have a new favorite,
u-prevent.com.
That’s just the letter U, dash,
prevent (P-R-E-V-E-N-T)
dot com.
It’s free and endorsed
by the European Society
of Cardiology.
Not only does it give you
a 10-year risk estimate,
and a lifetime risk estimate,
but it estimates how long
you may have before the event
and, best of all,
you can then toggle
various treatment options
to see what may happen
to your risk if you follow them,
like what happens
if you stop smoking,
or increase your step count,
or start a statin.
If this woman does nothing,
then her 8.6% ten-year risk
would likely merit a statin,
but whether or not the overall
benefit-harm balance
justifies the use
of a medication
for an individual patient
cannot be determined
by a guidelines committee,
a healthcare system,
or even the attending physician.
Instead, it is
the individual patient
who has a fundamental right
to decide
whether or not to take a drug
is worthwhile.
It’s your body, your choice;
so, let’s go through the pros
and cons
so you can decide
for yourself, next.